Guide to the Peter Goin photographs, 1987-2006 and undated RL.00459
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Peter Goin photographs
1987-2006 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Goin, Peter, 1951-
RL.00459
8.0 Linear Feet 8 boxes Approximately 1451 items
Collection consists of photographs by Peter Goin on the theme of the interactions and the connections between people and the natural world, and the way people manage, perceive, and represent "nature." The images depict altered and artificial landscapes featuring beaches, canals, farm fields, rivers, prescribed burns and reforestation sites, zoos, an abandoned town, and other places. They were shot in various locations, predominantly in North and South Carolina and Virginia, but also in Alabama, Georgia, central Florida, Arizona, California, Tennessee, and Nevada. The project resulted in a book, Humanature (1996) and an exhibit. Image formats include 16x20 inch exhibit-quality color prints, accompanied by negatives, black-and-white work prints, and book illustration prints. Research, correspondence, and other publication materials are also included in the collection. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts, Duke University.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research; however, photocopying is restricted. Access to original negatives only by permission of curator of Archive of Documentary Arts.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Peter Goin photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 1992-1994; other materials received as a gift in 2014 and 2016.
Collection Overview
Collection chiefly consists of photographs by Peter Goin on the theme of the interactions and the connections between people and the natural world, and the way people manage, perceive, and represent "nature." The exhibit-quality color prints (16x20 inches) and black-and-white work prints (chiefly 8x10) feature images taken Goin from 1991-1992 while he was Artist-In-Residence at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. They depict altered and artificial landscapes such as beaches, canals, farm fields, rivers and dams, managed forests, a scale model of a river, zoos, an abandoned town (Ellenton, S.C.), and other places. In these settings, people can be seen replanting trees, building ditches, hunting, or simply surveying their surroundings. Other formats include negatives, two slides, and book illustration prints. The collection also includes research, correspondence, publicity, and other materials deriving from the book Humanature.
The images were shot in various locations, predominantly in North and South Carolina and Virginia, but also in Alabama, Georgia, central Florida, Arizona, California, and Tennessee. Locations in North Carolina include Durham, the NC Zoological Park, Duke Forest, the Carnivore Preservation Trust, Outer Banks beaches, the Chatooga and Nantahala Rivers, and the Appalachian mountains near Highlands. There is also one image from Nevada. A selection was published in Goin's book, Humanature, published by University of Texas Press in 1996, and the project also generated a traveling exhibit of the same name.
A group of copy prints included in the collection were used illustrate Goin's book. These are historic images from the 1930s through the 1980s, many taken to document the work of state-run programs. As with Goin’s own work, they also show human-altered landscapes such as reforestation sites, canals, beach erosion replanting sites, and others. A few images appear to be from the 1950s and are of schoolchildren in Aiken, South Carolina. Other locations include Durham, N.C.’s Duke Forest, the Colorado River, beaches, and western deserts.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts, Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
Organized in series by format: Negatives, Photographic Prints, and Papers.
Environment (Art); Environmental management -- Pictorial works; Landscape photography -- Exhibitions; Nature -- effect of human beings on; People and nature -- Pictorial works; Reclamation of land; Alabama -- Pictorial works; Arizona -- Pictorial works; California -- Pictorial works; Florida -- Pictorial works; Georgia -- Pictorial works; North Carolina -- Pictorial works; South Carolina -- Pictorial works; Tennessee -- Pictorial works; Virginia -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Negatives (photographic); Color slides; Goin, Peter, 1951-; Goin, Peter, 1951-; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Negatives, 1991-1992 and undated, 147 negatives
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains a mostly complete collection of 4x5 inch negatives used to create the work and exhibit prints. While a large majority of the negatives have corresponding black-and-white and color prints, about ten have no prints. The full text and identifying numbers for all captions as well as additional information about the project can be found in Goin's notebook pages housed in this collection.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Access to original negatives only by permission of the Curator of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
  - Negatives N1-N46, N48-N60, N62A-N75C, N78-N85, N87, N89-N94, N96, N98-101, N103-N111, N113-N118, N120-N126, N135L-N136R, N139, N141, N145-N145A, N149-N150, N160, N162-N163, N165, CB31, CG32 (Box 1)
  - Negatives, 4x5 inch, front matter illustrations for Humanature, undated, 11 items (Box 8)
- Photographic prints, 1990s and undated; 340 prints
  Chiefly consists of exhibit and work prints produced by Peter Goin for the project "Humanature." Corresponding negative numbers are marked on reverse side of prints. There are several prints with identification numbers CB31 and CG32. Original captions have been retained; ellipses indicate additional text in long captions that has not been included. The full text for all captions as well as additional information about the project can be found in the notebook pages housed in the Papers Series.
  The series is concluded by a group of 81 copy prints and other items labeled as "front-matter illustrations" for the book, Humanature.
  - Work prints, black-and-white, circa 1991-1992, 146 prints
    Scope and Contents
    The most complete set of printed images with captions is found in this subseries of black-and-white 8x10 inch work prints used by Goin to select frames for larger exhibit prints. All captions are original. Ellipses indicate text found in very long captions that was not included here.
    - Horsepasture River near Highlands, NC: Abandoned and water-reclaimed road, national forest (Box 2, Print N1)
    - Audubon Swamp near Charleston, SC... (Box 2, Print N2)
    - Hollyberry Lake, NC: Overgrown and abandoned spillway near Highlands, NC (Box 2, Print N3)
    - Hollyberry Lake, NC: Overflow drain at lake near Highlands, NC (Box 2, Print N4)
    - Man-made flies (Box 2, Print N5)
    - Duke Forest: Overgrown erosion gully (Box 2, Print N6)
    - Artificial sand dune with fan at North Carolina Museum of Life and Science (Box 2, Print N7)
    - Outdoor "toilet" along Horsepasture River (Box 2, Print N8)
    - Tulip poplar monoculture established after clear-cutting national forest near Highlands, NC (Box 2, Print N9)
    - Cut tree and overgrown stump near bridge to Horsepasture River, NC (Box 2, Print N10)
    - Fabric-draped tree along Horsepasture River, NC (Box 2, Print N11)
    - Human-made tree for North Carolina Zoological Park, made by zoo designer Louis Bradley... (Box 2, Print N12)
      (2 prints)
    - Man-made rocks at black bear exhibit, NC Zoological Park (Box 2, Print N13)
    - Man-made armature for rocks at wolf landscape, NC Zoological Park (see N116) (Box 2, Print N14)
    - Future site of prairie dog landscape at NC Zoological Park (Box 2, Print N15)
    - Albino rainbow trout: Walhalla National Fish Hatchery and the US Fish and Wildlife Service, Department of the Interior (Box 2, Print N16)
    - Stop sign and kudzu covered trees in winter with approaching winter storm near Georgia-NC boundary (Box 2, Print N17)
    - Abandoned and overgrown road three miles from Chatooga River, NC (Box 2, Print N18)
    - This creek is measured and drains into the Chatooga River, NC (Box 2, Print N19)
    - Students in Parks and Recreation class from Clemson University... (Box 2, Print N20)
    - Firewood Tree Totem at secluded creek near Transylvania County Line, NC (Box 2, Print N21)
    - (Uncaptioned print) (Box 2, Print N22)
    - Black walkway across Nantahala River, NC (Box 2, Print N23)
    - River markers, Nantahala River, NC (Box 2, Print N24)
    - Dry Falls, NC (near Highlands): Falls and Fence (Box 2, Print N25)
    - Boundary marked trees near Highlands, NC (Box 2, Print N26)
    - Man-made falls at Sequoyah Lake and dam, Highlands, NC... (Box 2, Print N27)
    - Plastic fern grove in national forest near Highlands, NC (Box 2, Print N28)
    - ...Two views of helicopter stocking of Chatooga River...stocking one year old rainbow trout... (Box 2, Print N29A-B)
    - Judaculla Rock covered with gazebo near East Laport, NC... (Box 2, Print N30)
    - ..."H-7 shack" on Howard Creek within the Bad Creek Hydro-electric power station in North Carolina...two Duke Power employees, John Garton (right) and Allen Nicholson (left) observe... (Box 2, Print N31)
    - Revegetation field called Spoil Area 5 within the Bad Creek Power station. It is planted with sawtooth oaks, red and white clover, and sericea... (Box 2, Print N32)
    - "Caution-Avoid" sign at Joyce Kilmer Memorial Forest (Box 2, Print N33)
    - ...Two hunters, Eric Sellers (left) and Niel Morgan are waiting for their dogs to return after hunting "bear and boar" in Joyce Kilmer Memorial Forest (Box 2, Print N34)
    - Chimp climbing tree (see N12) (Box 2, Print N35)
    - Carving, or weathering, man-made rock (Box 2, Print N36)
    - Human-made tornado at NC Museum of Life and Science... (Box 2, Print N37)
    - Beach wall, Ft. Fisher, south of Kure Beach, NC (man-made rocks, including brick debris, concrete) (Box 2, Print N38)
    - Sea wall, south of Wrightsville Beach, NC... (Box 2, Print N39)
    - End of the road, ocean damage north of Surf City, NC (Box 2, Print N40)
    - Abandoned pier building, ocean damage, north of Surf City, NC (Box 2, Print N41)
    - Lenny Olivaros and Juan Angel Gomez planting a water oak (quercus nigra) in waterfowl area next to human-made swamp at NC Zoological Park (Box 2, Print N42)
    - Lenny Olivaros (L) and Juan Angel Gomez carrying (planting) Laurel Oak (quercus laurifolia) into waterfowl area next to human-made swamp at NC Zoological Park. Robert Evans, the project foreman, is directing (Box 2, Print N43)
    - Bob McCandless and helpers are "shooting" cement onto rock forms in the desert area of the North American Landscape section of the NC Zoological Park (Box 2, Print N44)
    - Numbered Trees in Duke Forest (rainy day)... (Box 2, Print N45)
    - Sign in Duke Forest... (Box 2, Print N46)
    - Arbor at Roanoke Island within Ft. Raleigh National Historic Site... (Box 2, Print N48)
    - (Sand colored) large sandbags positioned to act as seabreak in front of Cape Hatteras lighthouse (Box 2, Print N49)
    - Discarded Christmas trees in parking lot of picnic area at Ft. Macon... (Box 3, Print N50)
    - "Shooting" cement onto artificial rocks at grizzly exhibit at NC Zoo ("unshot" rocks in foreground) (Box 3, Print N51)
    - Welding work (inside armature) for rocks at grizzly exhibit... (Box 3, Print N52)
    - Orange fences mark "nature areas" at NC Zoo (Box 3, Print N53)
    - Four women who work at the NC Zoo in the design department... (Box 3, Print N54)
    - Human-made peregrine falcon nest within a steep rock face at Lake Jocassee reservoir area, upstate South Carolina...includes three views...the nest and two views from different distances of the workmen (Box 3, Print N55 and N55A-B)
      (3 prints)
    - ...These two photographs are from the town of Ellenton [S.C.]. The front steps of the school are still visible under the growth. The front porch of Dr. Lucius Bailey's house is all that remains... (Box 3, Print N56A-B)
    - "Wildlife Food Plot" sign from the Duke Power Company (Box 3, Print N57)
    - Wild turkey, largemouth bass, wood duck, and white-tailed deer waiting for final painting and customer pick up, McKinsey Wildlife Taxidermy, Anderson, SC... (Box 3, Print N58)
    - Prescribed burn of longleaf pine forest within Sandhills State Forest near Cheraw, SC (Box 3, Print N59)
    - Accidental burn along roadside of longleaf pine forest within Sandhills State Forest near Cheraw, SC (Box 3, Print N60)
    - Two views of wild turkey trapping operation in Florence County, SC... (Box 3, Print N62)
    - ...Called the "artificial," "fake," "phony," or "dummy" deer by the public, the decoy was the direct result of more than 377 deer poaching citations... (Box 3, Print N63)
    - ...Called the "artificial," "fake," "phony," or "dummy" deer by the public, the decoy was the direct result of more than 377 deer poaching citations... (Box 3, Print N64)
    - Numerous views of active burn conducted at Peachtree Rock Preserve by Nature Conservancy personnel in South Carolina... (Box 3, Print N65)
    - Portrait of burn personnel... (Box 3, Print N66)
    - The day after the prescribed burn. Originally, discarded Christmas trees were placed in this drainage area to arrest erosion (Box 3, Print N67)
    - The day after the prescribed burn...working to eliminate a smoldering stump... (Box 3, Print N68)
    - Hydro-seeding restored landscape. Owen Parton is using a high-pressure hose to apply fertilizer, lime, a mixture of clover and fescue grass seed with mulch (Box 3, Print N69)
    - Erosion control at Coon Branch, Duke Power Co. property. Rock lined drainage designed to prevent silt from clogging the Whitewater River (Box 3, Print N70)
    - Power House and Pilot Tunnel (Box 3, Print N71)
    - Discharge or tail-race tunnel with human-made rock walls, Duke Power Co.... (Box 3, Print N72)
    - Red silt in drainage ditch, Duke Power Co. (Box 3, Print N73)
    - Lone tree in clear-cut area after recent reforestation effort near Emporia, Virginia (Box 3, Print N74)
    - ...Numerous views of Virginia Beach City beach restoration and maintenance, 1992. Beach site is at Atlantic and 35th Street access... (Box 3, Print N75B-C)
    - Artificial landscape at 22nd and Pacific Avenue (Jungle Golf), Virginia Beach, VA (Box 3, Print N78)
    - Walk-ramp and rain gauge at flow-through marsh, east side of Pool B, Kissimmee River system (Box 3, Print N79)
    - The Kissimmee River channel denied water flow to the oxbow portions of the historic (or prior) river... (Box 3, Print N80)
    - Weir #3, Kissimmee River... (Box 3, Print N81)
    - Hunter's camp and hog's foot at Oak Hammock along the historic section of the Kissimmee River (Box 3, Print N82)
    - Rope swing at hunter's camp, Oak Hammock, Kissimmee River (Box 3, Print N83)
    - ...Weir #2 in front of "Charlie" bombing range... (Box 3, Print N84L-R)
      (3 triptych prints)
    - Camp Yahoo north near Weir #3 along Kissimmee River... (Box 3, Print N85)
    - Dave Darrow, Wildlife Biologist, at the Highway 60 check station for the Three Lakes Wildlife Management Area bordering Lake Kissimmee, central Florida... (Box 3, Print N87)
    - ...Recreational boats at Silver Glen Springs, Ocala National Forest and Lake George, central Florida (near Orlando) (Box 3, Print N89L-R)
    - Parking area construction for public beach access #4 Onslow County, NC... (Box 3, Print N92)
    - 24 Hour dredging and beach restoration operation, Topsail Beach, NC (Box 3, Print N93)
    - "Buried Telephone Cable" flags along Topsail Beach, NC (Box 3, Print N94)
    - ...Hamster courtesy of Pet Mania, Durham, NC (Box 3, Print N96)
    - Best general view of North Potato Creek Falls and cement truck, Ducktown, Tennessee (Box 3, Print N98)
    - ...Early reforestation trees near Ducktown (Box 3, Print N99)
    - ...Tennessee Chemical Company mining tower view of landscape looking towards Copperhill, Tennessee. Restoration pine now covers the landscape (Box 4, Print N100L-R)
      (2 diptych prints)
    - The Burra Burra Mine caved in fifty years ago, leaving a massive (and dangerous) water-filled pit... (Box 4, Print N101)
    - Burnt kudzu vines and telephone wires, Copperhill, TN (Box 4, Print N103)
    - Dormant kudzu covered landscape, Copperhill, TN (Box 4, Print N104)
    - Roadkill. The possum, the only marsupial in North America... (Box 4, Print N105)
    - Male Eld Deer (Thai) on urine collection platform, National Zoo Conservation and Research Center, Front Royal, Virginia (Box 4, Print N106)
    - Male Eld Deer (David) with Linwood Williamson, Wildlife Technician, in outdoor yard, National Zoo Conservation and Research center, Front Royal, Virginia (Box 4, Print N107)
    - ...This photograph documents one of the artificially inseminated Eld Deer (Vanessa) on the weighing platform with Linwood Willimason and Dennis Hosack... (Box 4, Print N108)
    - ...This photograph documents young binturongs (Arctictis binturong, Southeast Asia) eating fruit against the chain link fence... (Box 4, Print N109)
    - Nancy Schonwalter, member of the core staff at CPT, frames a jaguar... (Box 4, Print N110)
    - The Orange County, North Carolina jail was moved to the Carnivore Trust's grounds to provide the required cage strength for Declaudine, a Malayan Sun Bear... (Box 4, Print N111)
    - Dr. Michael Bleyman, founder of the Carnivore Preservation Trust, plays with Romeo and two female tigers, Marci and Charlotte... (Box 4, Print N113)
    - Overgrown black leopard cage at CPT (Box 4, Print N114)
    - Feeding fruit to tayra (Galera barbara)... (Box 4, Print N115)
    - Rock nearly completed at Zoo (see N14) (Box 4, Print N116)
    - Drain in swamp at NC Zoo (Box 4, Print N117)
    - Steve Runnfeldt, Assistant Design Technician, mixing paint for rocks at desert area, NC Zoo (Box 4, Print N118)
    - Human-made rocks, NC Zoo (see N51) (Box 4, Print N120)
    - Rephotographs of Virginia Beach during Memorial Day weekend: (letters coincide with N75A-C) (Box 4, Print N121A-C)
    - View looking south from top of Thunderbird Hotel, Virginia Beach, during Memorial Day weekend (Box 4, Print N122)
    - Kudzu and wire along Intersate Highway 40 west of Durham, NC (Box 4, Print N123)
    - ...Kudzu and snake(s) along NC Highway 421 west of Winston-Salem (Box 4, Print N124L-R)
    - Geer Cemetery 1877-1944, Durham, NC (Box 4, Print N125A-B)
    - Kissimmee River Research Project Model Study at the University of California at Berkeley, CA...Roger Manley poses to indicate the scale (Box 4, Print N126)
    - ...This company-owned residential district, now abandoned, was named the Stargo townsite... (Box 4, Print N135L-R)
    - ...The Clifton-Morenci Pit, one of the largest open-pit copper mines in North America... (Box 4, Print N136L-R)
    - A tailings plateau near Miami, Arizona (Box 4, Print N139)
    - Pseudoliths along road near Clifton, Arizona... (Box 4, Print N141)
    - Waterfall at Pinal Creek (Box 4, Print N145)
    - Pipes at Pinal Creek at Globea dn Miami, Arizona (Box 4, Print N145A)
    - ...Three-acre, enclosed ecological system in the foothills of the Santa Catalina Mountains north of Tucson Arizona...Biosphere 2... (Box 4, Print N149)
    - The Pacific Ocean at Cabrillo National Monument at San Diego, California (Box 4, Print N150)
    - Workers from the Los Angeles Conservation Corps use a water-blaster to clean graffiti off rocks along a tributary to the West fork of the San Gabriel River in the Angeles National Forest... (Box 4, Print N160)
    - Painted rocks and engraved trees along the West fork of the San Gabriel River in the Angeles National Forest, California (Box 4, Print N162)
    - Toxic Nation, Angeles National Forest (Box 4, Print N163)
    - Heavy smog over the Angeles National Forest near Los Angeles, California (Box 4, Print N165)
    - Watering the sand at Palm Desert, California (Box 4, Print CB31)
    - A boy in red fishes in the stagnant water on the other side of the Rye Patch Dam in north-central Nevada after the final 800-acre feet of water was drained for irrigation, 1992 (Box 4, Print CG32)
  - Exhibit prints, color, 1991-1992, 113 prints
    Color prints measure 16x20 inches and are marked on reverse with corresponding negative numbers. Captions for images found only in the color series and not in the black-and-white prints series are written out below. Otherwise, a complete itemized caption list is found in the black-and-white work prints series.
    - Color prints N2, N5-N6, N8, N10-N11, N14, N16-N21, N24, N28, N29A-N36, N39-N42, N44-N46, N48, N50, N53-N56, N58, N60, N62-N64 (captions are listed in black-and-white prints series) (Box 5)
    - Numerous views of active burn conducted at Peachtree Rock Preserve by Nature Conservancy personnel in South Carolina... (Box 6, Print N65)
      (5 prints)
    - Color prints N72-N74 (captions for these prints are listed in black and white prints series) (Box 6)
    - ...Numerous views of Virginia Beach City beach restoration and maintenance, 1992. Beach site is at Atlantic and 35th Street access... (Box 6, Print 75A-C)
    - Color prints N79, N81-N82, N84-N85, N87, N89L-N89R (captions are listed in black and white prints series) (Box 6)
    - Boy Scout Troops 401 and 447 earning their canoe merit badges at Buck Lake, Ocala National Forest, Florida... (Box 6, Print N90)
    - Public beach access structure north of Surf City in Onslow County, NC (Box 6, Print N91)
    - 24 hour dredging and beach restoration operation, Topsail Beach, NC (Box 6, Print N93)
    - Color prints N92, N94, N96, N98-N101, N103-N111, N113-N117, N121C, N124L-N124R, N126, N135L-N136R, N139, N141, N145-N145A, N149-N150, N160, N162-N163, N165, CB31, CG32 (captions are listed in black and white prints series) (Box 6)
  - Book illustration copy prints for Humanature, 1990s and undated
    Label on original box refers to "front-matter illustrations." They are presented in a mix of 8x10 and 5x7 inch glossy prints, 5x7 inch older prints, a smaller color print, and two color slides. Some prints have captions, illustration numbers, and negative numbers; a few have editing instructions. Scenes are of human-altered landscapes from the 1930s to the 1980s.
    - Copy prints and other items, black-and-white and color, 81 prints; 2 slides (Box 8)
- Papers, 1987-2006 and undated; 1 folders
  Houses pages from a notebook of information assembled by the photographer, which describes the project "Humanature," and is accompanied by a full list of captions. Captions given in the section below are taken from notebook, and represent images from Humanature that are not in the collection.
  - Notebook assembled by Peter Goin, 1990s
    - Notebook pages, 1 folders (Box 5)
  - Print captions listed in notebook that do not have existing prints or negatives in the collection
    - Numerous views of Virginia Beach City beach restoration. These views represent the dredging and bulldozing near 7th along the Boardwalk... (Box 5, Print N76)
    - Beach restoration project for Virginia Beach City; Lynnhaven Inlet Sand Stockpile and truck loading operation (Box 5, Print N77)
    - Pool A, small oxbow denied running water after the channel was completed in 1971... (Box 5, Print N86)
    - Two-spot West African Palm Civet poses for the camera... (Box 5, Print N112)